Guide to the John James Audubon artwork, 1835-2002.
Audubon, John James artwork, 1835-2002.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
John James Audubon artwork, 1829-2002, 1829-1860 (bulk)
Audubon, John James, 1785-1851.
6721
6.3 cubic feet.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes loose prints from Audubon books, The birds of America (double elephant folio of 1827-1838 and a subsequent octavo edition) and The viviparous quadrupeds of North America (1846-1854), as well as later reproductions of Audubon prints.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection includes loose prints from Audubon books, The birds of America (double elephant folio of 1827-1838 and a subsequent octavo edition) and The viviparous quadrupeds of North America (1846-1854).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Audubon, John James, 1785-1851. Birds of America.; Audubon, John James, 1785-1851. Viviparous quadrupeds of North America.; Audubon, Lucy Green Bakewell, 1788-1874; Havell, Robert, 1793-1878; Bien, Julius, 1826-1909; Cornell University. Laboratory of Ornithology.
Subjects:
Birds--North America--Pictorial works.; Mammals--North America--Pictorial works.; Ornithological illustration.; Ornithology.; Birds in art
Form/genre terms:
Engravings--United States--19th century.; Lithographs.; Chromolithographs.; Hand coloring.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
By appointment only.
RELATED MATERIAL
The Waldemar H. Fries Audubon research papers, #3427 also contains original and reproductions of Audubon prints.
The Laboratory of Ornithology artwork collection, #17-2-3522 and the Louis Agassiz Fuertes papers, #2662 also contain artwork on deposit from Cornell's Laboratory of Ornithology
CONTAINER LIST
- Florida Jay - No. 47, Plate 233 - 0603 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Octavo edition
- Cedar Bird, or Cedar Waxwing - No. 50, Plate 246 - 0604 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mallard - No. 77, Plate 385 - 0605 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Evening Grosbeak - No. 42, Plate 207 - 0606 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Snow Lark Bunting - No. 31, Plate 155 - 0607 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Summer Red-bird - No. 42, Plate 208 - 0608 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Yellow Crowned Night Heron - No. 73, Plate 364 - 8005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Fork-tailed Flycatcher - No. 11, Plate 52 - 8025 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tell-tale Godwit or Snipe - Plate 308 - RMC, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Uncolored restrike of an 1836 plate.
- Tell-tale Godwit or Snipe - Plate 308 - RMC (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Purple Finch - Plate 4 - RMC (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Ivory-billed Woodpecker - No. 14, Plate LXVI - RMC (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Color Reproduction - Audubon Centennial Edition by R.E. Hall. P.P. 2/5
- Ruby-throated Hummingbird - RMC, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Chromolithograph by J. Bien
- Great White Heron - No. 57, Plate CCLXXXI - 8003, 65.4 x 50.2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Reduced black and white reproduction: "Reproduced at three fifths size from the original plate in the collection of the American Museum of Natural History."
- White-throated Sparrow - Plate VIII, No. II - 8002, 70.8 x 50.7 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Engraved by Lizars. Colored by Havell.
- Swallow-Tailed Hawk - No. 15-3, Plate 18 - 8008, 1860; 102.0 x 68.9 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- White-Eyed Flycatcher or Vireo - No. 15-5, Plate 240 and Red-Eyed Vireo - No. 15-6, Plate 243 - 8009, 1860; 101.9 x 68.7 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  Double elephant folio. Chromolithograph by J. Bien, both on a single sheet
- Yellow-Crowned Heron - No. 15-2, Plate 364 - 0601, 1860; 99.5 x 69.0 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Chromolithograph by J. Bien. Attached to acidic backing.
- Song Sparrows - No. 5, Plate 25 - 8001, 70.5 x 50.6 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Double elephant folio. Havell Print.
- Indigo-Birds - No. 15, Plate 74 - 8000, 1829; 70.9 x 50.7 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Double elephant folio. Engraved, Printed, Colored by R. Havell. Attached to acidic backing.
- Warbling Flycatcher - No. 24, Plate CXVIII - 8006, 72.3 x 53.6 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Palm Warbler - No. 33, Plate CLXIII - 8007, 1833; 72.1 x 53.3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Double elephant folio. Havell Print. Possibly a later restrike of a 1833 print
- Semipalmated Sandpiper - No. 81, Plate CCCCV - 8013, 1838; 94.3 x 63.9 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Double elephant folio
- Frigate Pelican - No. 55, Plate CCLXXI - 8012, 96.1 x 63.8 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Double elephant folio - Date corner torn off. Attached to acidic backing.
- American Sparrow Hawk - No. 29, Plate CXLII - 0602, 91.9 x 64.7 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Double elephant folio. Engraved, Printed, Colored by R. Havell.
- Hutchins's Barnacle Goose - No. 56, Plate CCLXXVII - 8010B, 61.0 x 50.8 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Reduced black and white reproduction: "Reproduced at four fifths size from the original plate in the collection of the American Museum of Natural History."
- Says Least Shrew - No. 14, Plate LXX - 8019, 1845; 68.8 x 54.2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Bowen Print
- Franklins Marmot Squirrell - No. 17, Plate LXXXIV - 8020, 1846; 70.0 x 55.4 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Dusky Squirrell - No. 24, Plate CXVII - 8021, 69.7 x 55.2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- The Camas Rat - No. 29, Plate CXLII - 8023, 1848; 68.7 x 54.0 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Hutchins's Barnacle Goose - No. 56, Plate CCLXXVII - 8010, 1958; 81.7 x 66.1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Full size black and white reproduction: "Struck from the original Havell engraving to commemorate the 75th Anniversary Meeting of the American Ornithologists' Union, held at the American Museum of Natural History, New York, in October 1958."
- Swallow-Tailed Hawk - No. 15, Plate 72 - 8004, 1829; 98.9 x 65.5 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  Double elephant folio. J. Bien print.
- Ferruginous Thrush - No. 24, Plate CXVI - 8018, 98.5 x 66.2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Mocking Bird - No. 5, Plate XXI - 8016, 96.5 x 64.1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  Double elephant folio. Engraved, Printed, and Coloured by R Havell.
- Chuck-Wills Widow - No. 11, Plate LII - 8017, 96.5 x 64.8 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Engraved, Printed, and Coloured by R Havell.
- Swamp Sparrow - No. 15, Plate LXIV - 8024, 96.5 x 64.2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- White-Crowned Pigeon - No. 36, Plate CLXXVII - 8015, 1829; 96.5 x 64.6 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Audubon elephant folio Frontispiece: Birds of America, from Original Drawings by John James Audubon. Volume III - 8014 (Volume Oversized)
  An original binding of an elephant folio with all the drawings removed. Includes the frontspiece.